Hey, hey, and welcome back to Living in
Central Texas. Have you had your eye on
the Temple, Texas area and are wondering
if new construction or resale is a
better choice for you? Well, then stick
with me today because I'll be giving you
a sidebyside comparison of two very
similarly priced homes, one new
construction, one resale, right here in
Temple, Texas.
Hi, I'm Andrea Dudik and welcome back to
Living in Central Texas. I help people
from all over the place relocate to and
from the central Texas area. If you're
new to my channel, don't forget to like,
subscribe, and click the bell
notification so that you can stay
uptodate on all things real estate here
in Central Texas.
a little sneak peek into the two homes
we'll be checking out today. Our first
is going to be a resale home on the west
side of Temple built in 2019 priced at
$3099.
It recently had a $10,000 price
reduction. And then our new construction
home, stick around to see it, is going
to be on the east side of Temple. Very
similarly sized. Um, built in 2025,
brand spanking new, never lived in, has
a bunch of really great incentives,
including builder warranties, and that
one is built by Flint Rock and priced at
314895.
Even though they are very similarly
priced, some of the reflection in that
price has to do with location and school
district. Both are in Temple. This
resale um in city of Temple is actually
Belton ISD. And what we find is that
homes on the west side of 35 and in
Belton ISD price per per square foot's a
little bit higher. I do think this can
tend to be a more desirable area for a
lot of people. Doesn't necessarily mean
it's better, but there is that
difference in price per square foot and
I think that's why our new construction
home is going to be on the east side of
Temple Temple.
First stop is going to be this Omega
construction resale home built in 2019.
It's just over 1,800 square feet, four
bed, three bath.
When you walk into the home, you
immediately notice the grand foyer area.
This is a super split floor plan with
two bedrooms and a full bath being at
the front of the home. The third bed and
bath being more towards the middle of
the home and the primary bedroom and
bathroom being at the rear of the home
just off of the living room.
All of the bedrooms have carpet and the
wet areas, main living spaces, and
kitchen all have a square brown tile.
This home utilizes a lot of warm tones,
the walls being a beige, brown carpet,
and of course the brown tile throughout.
There are blinds throughout the home and
fans in all of the bedrooms, which isn't
necessarily something that comes
standard in new construction.
All of the bathrooms have tile floor,
brown cabinets, and this speckled
granite countertop.
The kitchen has a ton of cabinet space,
a large center island overlooking the
living room, and electric appliances. A
question I often get asked is, is there
gas here? In some areas, there is gas
available. if gas cooking is a must for
you. Typically, most communities do have
electric stoves, though, but not all. If
this is important to you, make sure to
highlight it since it's not necessarily
something that comes standard in our
area. The pantry on this home is
fantastic. Just off the living space is
your laundry room
and primary bedroom. The lighting in
here is great, and the furniture helps
give a really good idea of space.
The backyard is really wide. It has a
small covered patio with a concrete slab
addition and no rear neighbors, which is
a plus.
And I often forget to include footage of
the garage, so here you go. This home
comes with a Westinghouse water
filtration and softener system. Again,
those two things are not standard in new
construction. You'll also see the water
heaters in the garage as well.
Okay, so this was an Omega build. Omega
is one of our major production builders
here in the area. They build a beautiful
home and uh there's always some design
elements with them that kind of stand
out that when I walk in, I can just tell
right off the bat that it's an Omega.
One of them is their use of tile. They
use a lot more tile than a lot of
builders. So, if you can see the
flooring, it's just some square tiles.
They have tile backsplashes. They have
tile uh often a lot in the bathrooms.
So, that's one thing. And one thing that
I really appreciate is the large
hallways. Everything feels really open
in their homes. So, you can see this
threshold here, this entrance from the
foyer, the hall into the kitchen and
dining space. It's very open and large.
So, I think that that's really good just
even for accessibility
um regardless. Oh, and they also use a
lot of window um a lot of use of good
window lighting.
This kitchen has a ton of cabinet space.
Got your brown cabinets.
This home in particular does come with a
fridge. Your microwave, stove, and
dishwasher are always going to convey.
They're considered built-in items. Um
the microwave, if it's not built-in, if
it's on the counter, it doesn't
automatically. And fridges are
negotiable. They have left it here. So,
that would be something that we'd write
in, but I it would typically stay in a
home like this. This home has been
staged, but it's a cutie, right? What do
you think?
Our second stop is this brand new
construction Flint Rock home in East
Temple. And this is a great deal. The
builder is offering an insanely low
interest rate right now, which they're
able to do with in-house lending, ton of
closing cost assistance, and anything
else I can help you get. So, um, this
builder is building in a lot of
different areas and a lot of different
price points. So, this is a great
entrylevel home priced at 314895,
but they're building in Temple, um,
Belton, Nolanville, Troy, Cedo, Lena,
um, a little bit of everywhere here in
Central Texas, and they're also building
some really, really cool duplexes. So,
if you're looking for opportunity in
general, and you like the feel and style
of this builder, give me a call. I can
get you inventory. I can tell you what
incentives and I can help you get the
best deal. So, really cool, really
pretty home. It is priced at 314,895,
just over 1,800 square ft. Built in
2025, 4 bed, three bath. This one in
particular is on a corner lot. These
homes are super modern. The colors are
beautiful. The elevations, which is the
front of the home, is going to be
different on each of these. This one's
black. The next one's white. They use a
mix of stone and brick as well as that
siding. So, really pretty. Uh just
really great curb appeal. Can't wait to
show you the inside. Let's go. Welcome
to this beautiful Flint Rock new
construction home. It's roughly 1854
square ft, four bed, three bath, and on
a corner lot. The floor plan is split
here as well. The first two bedrooms are
at the front of the home.
The walls throughout the home are white
carpet in the bedroom and vinyl plank
all through the main living spaces and
wet areas, including laundry room and
bathrooms. The third bedroom is super
functional, set up as a mother-in-law
style suite with a full bathroom inside
the bedroom and a walk-in closet. That
is something that I frequently get asked
for is a mother-in-law style suite with
a bedroom having that additional bedroom
for privacy for various life styles and
situations.
I love the gray granite and funky tile
surrounds in the bathrooms. This builder
always throws in some fun design
elements in every price point. In the
main living space, the electric
fireplace is the focal point.
[Music]
There's an eating kitchen with a really
pretty chandelier. The kitchen overlooks
the living space.
Everything is super neutral, cool toned
and clean with white cabinets, gray
granite countertops, brushed nickel
fixtures and hardware, and stainless
steel appliances.
The primary bedroom is wellsized and has
a ceiling fan. The primary bath features
dual vanities, white cabinets, the same
gray granite, and a walk-in shower.
The closet on this one is a goodiz
walk-in closet, but not as big as our
resale closet, but the spacing, room
sizes, and overall layout are pretty
comparable to our resale home that we
toured. The backyard features a small
covered patio, full saw and irrigation,
and a privacy fence.
And of course, with a new construction
home, you will typically get builder
warranties. While they vary from builder
to builder, it's pretty common to see
what we call a 1 to 10 warranty. That
one-year general builder warranty, which
is basically a bumperto-bumper warranty
on the home. Kind of covers everything
not cosmetic or um buyer related. uh
that first year, a 2-year major systems
electrical HVAC, which is your heating
and cooling systems, an electrical
warranty, and a 10-year foundation
warranty. Again, vary builder to
builder, but those are something that we
typically see in that range.
With a resale, um you do not get those
builder warranties, but you can ask for
a one-year home warranty credit in
negotiating your contract. If you're
thinking about moving here, be sure to
download the free relocation guide
below. It's packed with neighborhood
statistics, videos, and local insights.
Okay, that wraps up our tour of this
brand new construction Flint Rock home
here in the Northeast Temple, Texas
area. Again, totally different location
and vibe, but really, really awesome
price. This builder has just gotten
started in this community. There's a ton
of inventory and we are in a buyer
market at the moment. So, a lot of these
builders are offering insane incentives
to purchase one of their homes.
Drastically reduced interest rates. I've
seen as low as 4.99.
Um, a lot of builders are paying closing
costs. This builder is really good at
offering those incentives. So, I think
whether you're looking at resale or new
construction, there's a lot of
opportunity. There's just different
opportunity. A lot of buyers are
negotiating, I'm sorry, a lot of sellers
are negotiating heavily to get rid of
their homes and a lot of builders are
offering a lot of incentives. And of
course, don't forget to use your realtor
when purchasing a home because the sales
reps are fantastic, but they represent
the builder and the builder's interest.
And you really need someone representing
and advocating for you. can do things
like negotiate contracts, get you the
best deals, tell you about other
incentives, try and get things into the
home that the builder may not have
included or wanted to offer. And we are
here. We're seeing the market. We know
how to negotiate for you and what's
happening. And if you're relocating here
and you're doing new construction, it's
also really wonderful cuz I can do
things like get you regular photos and
videos and do all the fun stuff that you
can't do when you are here.
So, I'm really curious which one you
like. Tons of opportunity whichever
direction you go. If you'd like more
information on living in the Temple,
Belton, or General Central Texas area,
you can find all my contact information
below. You can also head on over to my
website livinginctx.com
where I have a really awesome
interactive map so you can get a really
good feel of the area and kind of
immerse yourself to everything central
Texas. Till next time, I'm Andrea Dudik.